<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<deck xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <title xml:lang="en">The Pictorial Key to the Tarot</title>
    <description xml:lang="en">
        <paragraph>
            <a xlink:href="https://www.sacred-texts.com/tarot/pkt/index.htm" xlink:type="simple" xlink:show="new">By Arthur Edward Waite</a>
            Although there were many Tarot decks prior to the Rider-Waite-Smith deck, and many after, none has gripped the popular imagination as much as this set. Waite covers the significance and deeper implications of each card, and gives practical instructions as to how to conduct a reading. The symbolism of the Rider-Waite-Smith deck is based on profound occult studies by Waite, and his exposition in this book of its use and meaning is unexcelled. This is a must-read for anyone who wants to understand the Tarot.--J. B. Hare
        </paragraph>
    </description>
    <card id="00">
        <description xml:lang="ru">
            <paragraph>
            Легким шагом, как будто земная твердь со всеми ее ухабами и рытвинами неспособна его удержать, юноша в богатой одежде на миг замер над краем пропасти средь горных вершин; взгляд его устремлен в голубую даль - скорее в бездонные небеса, нежели в открывающийся внизу путь. Он показан в стремительном движении, хотя в данный момент и замер в неподвижности; собака у его ног взметнулась в прыжке. Край разверзшейся перед ним пропасти не ужасает - впечатление такое, будто ангелы готовы вот-вот подхватить его, если он решится шагнуть в бездну. Его лицо светится умом и мечтательностью. В одной руке у него роза, в другой - драгоценный посох, на котором висит затейливо расшитая сума. Это принц из иного мира, странствующий в нашем - в полном блеске раннего свежего утра. Солнце, сияющее у него за спиной, знает, откуда он пришел, куда идет и как вернется другим путем много дней спустя. Это Дух в поиске Опыта. В этой карте собраны воедино многие символы Мистерий, что с высокой степенью достоверности опровергает все прежние ошибки и недоразумения.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            В своем «Пособии по картомантии» «Великий Восток» делает любопытное предположение о функции Мистического Глупца как участника процесса высшего гадания; однако для того, чтобы заставить его выполнить свое предназначение, требуются незаурядные дарования. Мы еще увидим, как ведет себя эта карта по общепринятым канонам гадания, и для тех, кто умеет видеть различия, это послужит лишним подтверждением того, что Старшим Арканам изначально не было места в искусстве гадательных игр, где карты используются как фишки с заранее заготовленными текстами. Впрочем, нам очень немногое известно об обстоятельствах, сопутствовавших зарождению этого искусства. Согласно общепринятым толкованиям, Глупец означает плоть, чувственную жизнь, а кое-кто (явно сатирически) называл эту фигуру Алхимиком, т.е. тем, кто демонстрирует крайнюю стадию глупости.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            Прорицательные значения: Безумство, мания, экстравагантность, опьянение, бред, лихорадочное возбуждение, невольное предательство.
            Перевернутая карта: Небрежность, отсутствие» распределение, беспечность, апатия, ничтожность» тщеславие.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="01">
        <description xml:lang="ru">
            <paragraph>
            Перед нами юноша в одеянии мага, ликом подобный Аполлону, с уверенной улыбкой на устах и блеском в очах. Над головой у него мистический знак Святого Духа - знак жизни в виде бесконечной ленты, которая образует лежащую восьмерку. Его талию опоясывает змея, кусающая себя за хвост. Большинству людей этот символ знаком как символ бесконечности, и в данном случае он указывает на бесконечность духовного совершенствования. Правая рука Мага с жезлом воздета к небесам, левая указывает вниз, на землю. Хорошо известный в наивысших степенях Учрежденных Мистерий, этот двойной жест символизирует нисхождение благодати, добродетели и света из верхнего мира в мир нижний. Таким образом, в образный строй всей карты заложена идея обладания Духовными Силами и Дарованиями и их передачи. На столе перед Магом, словно фишки некоей игры, разложены представляющие природные стихии символы четырех мастей Таро, которыми адепт распоряжается по своему усмотрению. Цветущие у его ног розы и лилии cyrbflos campi (полевые цветы) и lilium convalium (ландыши), превратившиеся в садовые цветы. Они служат наглядным примером благодатных результатов стремления к совершенству. Эта карта означает божественные побуждения в человеке, который сам есть образ и подобие Бога, и проявление воли к освобождению от единства с тем, что вверху. Это также цельность индивидуального бытия на всех уровнях, и в наивысшем значении - это мышление в его предельно сконцентрированной форме. Возвращаясь к тому, что я назвал символом жизни, и его взаимосвязи с числом 8, можно напомнить, что христианский гностицизм говорит о возрождении во Христе как о перемене «к Восьмерице». Это мистическое число соотносят с Небесным Иерусалимом, Землей, текущей молоком и медом, со Святым Духом и Царствием Небесным. Согласно учению мартинизма, 8 - это число Христа.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            Прорицательные значения: Мастерство, дипломатия, обращение, тонкость; недуг, боль, утрата, катастрофа, расставленные врагами западни; уверенность в себе, воля; сам Вопрошающий - если это мужчина.
            Перевернутая карта: Врач, Маг, психический недуг, позор, беспокойство.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="02">
        <description xml:lang="ru">
            <paragraph>
            У ее ног блестит полумесяц, голову венчает двурогая диадема с шаром посередине, а грудь украшает огромный солнечный крест. На свитке, который она держит в руках, можно прочесть слово Тора, означающее Высший закон, Тайный закон и второе значение Слова. Свиток отчасти прикрыт складками ее мантии, как бы намекая на то, что некоторые вещи лишь подразумеваются, но не говорятся в открытую. Она восседает меж двух колонн - белой и черной с буквами J и В - колонн у входа в мистический Храм, завеса которого видна за ее спиной. Завеса расшита узором из пальмовых листьев и плодов граната. Одеяния Жрицы струятся вдоль ее фигуры прозрачными волнами, а мантия излучает мерцающий свет. Ее именуют Оккультной Наукой на пороге Святилища Исиды, однако в действительности это Тайная Церковь, Дом Господа и человека. Она также представляет Второй Брак Князя, который уже не принадлежит миру сему; это духовная Невеста и Мать, дщерь звезд и Вышнего Сада Эдемского. Наконец, это Царица заимствованного света, но свет этот есть свет всего сущего. Это Луна, питаемая молоком Небесной Матери.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            В каком-то смысле это и сама Небесная Матерь - сиречь ее яркое отражение. Именно в этом значении отражения заключен подлинный и высший символический смысл ее имени Шекина - двойственное величие. Согласно учению Каббалы, Шекина присутствует и вверху, и внизу. В мире горнем она именуется Бина - Вселенский Разум, отражающий эманации мира дольнего. В мире дольнем это Малкут - в данном случае ее следует понимать как благословенное Царство, причем источником его благословения является Слава Господня. В мистическом смысле Шекина - это Духовная Невеста мужа праведного, и когда он читает Закон, она придает ему Божественный смысл. В определенном отношении эта карта является наивысшей картой Старших Арканов, облеченной наибольшей святостью.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            Прорицательные значения: Секреты, загадочность, неведомое на данный момент будущее; женщина, которая проявляет интерес к Вопрошающему-мужчине; сама Вопрошающая, если это женщина; молчание, целеустремленность; таинство, премудрость, наука.
            Перевернутая карта: Страсть, нравственное или физическое рвение, самомнение, поверхностные знания.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="03">
        <description xml:lang="ru">
            <paragraph>
            Величавая фигура, с царственным видом восседающая в богатых одеждах - как и подобает Дочери Небес и Земли. В ее диадеме сверкают двенадцать звезд» собранных в созвездие. На стоящем рядом щите изображен символ Венеры. Перед нею качает колосьями зреющая пшеница, а за спиной шумит водопад. Скипетр в ее руке увенчан шаром-символом земного мира. Это дольний Сад Эдемский, Земной Рай, - зримое обиталище человека. Это не Regina coeli [Царица Небесная], но refugium peccatorum [прибежище грешных], благодатная Матерь многих тысяч. В ряде аспектов она вполне справедливо описывается как желанием крылья его; как жена, облеченная в солнце*; как Gloria Mundi [мирская слава], как завеса Sanctum Sanctorum [святая святых]. Впрочем, могу добавить, что это отнюдь не обретшая крылья душа, если только весь символизм не истолковать в ином, непривычном направлении. Прежде всего она олицетворяет вселенскую плодовитость и внешнее значение Мира. Это вполне очевидно, ибо нет для человека более убедительного аргумента, нежели тот факт, что он был рожден женщиной; однако не она сама является носителем этой интерпретации.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            В иной системе понятий Императрица означает дверь или врата, через которые открывается вход в земную жизнь, словно в Сад Венеры. Тот же путь, что ве-дет за пределы этого сада, есть тайна, ведомая одной лишь Верховной Жрице, которую она открывает только избранным. Старые характеристики этой карты в большинстве своем глубоко ошибочны в истолковании символизма - к примеру, соотнесение Императрицы с понятиями Слова, Божественной природы. Троицы и т. д.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            Прорицательные значения: Плодотворность, действие, инициатива, долгожительство; нечто неизвестное, тайное; также трудности, сомнение, неведение.
            Перевернутая карта: Свет, истина, разрешение запутанных проблем, народные празднества; согласно другому толкованию - колебания, нерешительность.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="04">
        <description xml:lang="ru">
            <paragraph>
            Его скипетр имеет форму Сrux аnsata*, в левой руке уверенно покоится держава. Это монарх, коронованный по праву - властный, величественный,восседающий на троне, подлокотники которого украшены головами овнов. Он олицетворяет правление, осуществление и земную власть, будучи облеченным ее наивысшими естественными атрибутами. Иногда его изображают сидящим на каменном кубе, что, впрочем, вноситопределенную путаницу в символизм. Он представляет мужскую силу и мощь, которая находит отклик в Императрице, и в этом смысле именно он стремится открыть завесу Исиды. Тем не менее она остается virgointacta [«нетронутой девой»].
            * Крест с петлей, происходящий от египетского символа жизни - анх.
            Следует учитывать, что эта карта вместе с Императрицей не совсем буквально представляют супружество, хотя таковое подразумевается.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            На первый взгляд они олицетворяют земных царственных супругов, которые вознесены на тронах сильных мира сего; однако сверх того ощущается и намек на некое иное присутствие. Обе эти карты - и в первую очередь мужской персонаж - означают властителей вышнего царства, восседающих на троне разума. И здесь перед нами скорее властитель дум, нежели владыка земного мира. Оба персонажа на свой лад «богаты никому не ведомым опытом», но премудрость их - неосознанная, почерпнутая из вышнего мира. Император характеризуется как а) воплощенная воля, хоть это лишь одно из многих толкований, и 6) выражение добродетелей, присущих Абсолютному Бытию, - однако это уже чистая фантазия.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            Прорицательные значения: Стабильность, могущество, защита, осуществление; высокопоставленная особа; помощь, рассудок, убежденность; также власть и воля.
            Перевернутая карта: Благожелательность, сострадание, доверие; а также смятение в рядах врагов, препятствие, незрелость.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="05">
        <description xml:lang="ru">
            <paragraph>
            Его голову венчает тройная корона, а сам он восседает меж двух колонн, однако это не колонны Храма, охраняемого Верховной Жрицей. В левой руке у него скипетр с вершиной в виде тройного креста, правая же воздета в широко известном благословляющем жесте, который еще называют эзотерическим знаком, проводящим различие между проявленной и сокрытой частью учения. (В этой связи весьма примечательно, что Верховная Жрица не делает никаких жестов.) У его ног сложены крест-накрест ключи и преклонили колена двое священнослужителей в стихарях. Обычно его именуют Папой, что является частным проявлением более общего символизируемого им понятия. Это власть внешней религии, в то время как Верховная Жрица (Папесса) прежде всего представляет силу эзотерическую, сокрытую. К плачевным искажениям подлинных значений этой карты приложили руку все кому не лень. «Великий Восток» справедливо утверждает, что Первосвященник - это сила ключей экзотерической ортодоксальной доктрины и внешней стороны жизни, ведущей к этой доктрине. Но это, несомненно, не «князь оккультного учения», как предположил еще один комментатор.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            Это скорее summa totius teo-1оgiae [общая сумма теологии], перешедшая в крайне закоснелую форму. Впрочем, Иерофант также символизирует все, что праведно и священно с проявленной стороны. Как таковой, он является проводником благодати, принадлежащим, в отличие от мира Природы, миру человеческих установлений, а также проводником к спасению души всего человечества в целом. Это воплощение порядка и глава признанной иерархии, служащей отражением иного, высшего иерархического порядка. Но может случиться и так, что понтифик забудет о подлинной ценности своего символического статуса и начнет поступать так, словно ему по праву принадлежит все то, что означает его жест или представляет его символ. Это не философия, как ошибочно полагали, - разве что с теологической стороны. Это не вдохновение. И это не религия, хоть он и является одним из способов ее выражения.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            Прорицательные значения: Брачный союз, альянс, неволя, рабство; по другой версии - милосердие и доброта; вдохновение; человек, к которому Вопрошающий обращается за помощью.
            Перевернутая карта: Общество, взаимопонимание, согласие, чрезмерная доброта, слабость.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="06">
        <description xml:lang="ru">
            <paragraph>
            В лучах сияющего в зените солнца распростерло руки огромное крылатое существо, ниспосылая на землю свои энергии. На переднем плане две фигуры - мужская и женская, - не стыдящиеся своей наготы, подобно Адаму и Еве, обитавшим в земном раю земной плоти. За спиной мужчины возвышается Древо Жизни с двенадцатью плодами. Древо познания добра и зла с обвившим его змеем растет за спиной женщины. Эти фигуры говорят о юности, непорочности, невинности и любви, не затронутой грубым плотским желанием. Это карта человеческой любви во всей ее простоте, каковая представлена здесь как составная часть пути, и истины, и жизни. В самом высоком смысле эта карта символизирует таинство Завета.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            Что касается женской фигуры, то она означает влечение к чувственной жизни, в котором заложена идея Грехопадения, однако женщина скорее выступает орудием Тайного Закона Провидения, нежели добровольной, осознающей свои действия искусительницей. Именно через вмененный ей грех человек в конечном счете восстанет из греха, и только с ее помощью он сможет реализовать себя. Таким образом, эта карта является еще одним откровением великой тайны женского начала. От старых значений этой карты вкупе со старыми изображениями не остается камня на камне, но даже в истолковании последних эти значения либо грешили банальностью, либо заблуждались в символизме.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            Прорицательные значения: Влечение, любовь, красота, преодоленные испытания.
            Перевернутая карта: Неудача, прожектерство. Другое толкование говорит о развале брачного союза и всевозможных противоречиях.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="07">
        <description xml:lang="ru">
            <paragraph>
            В колеснице гордо возвышается царственная фигура с обнаженным мечом в руке. Плечи героя-победителя предположительно украшают Урим и Туммим*. Победитель даже неволе придал привлекательность; он есть победа, завоеванная на всех уровнях - в свершениях разума, в науке, прогрессе, в неких испытаниях, предшествующих посвящению. Следовательно, он сумел разрешить загадку сфинкса, и в этом отношении я согласен с трактовкой Элифаса Леви; потому-то и колесницу его влекут два сфинкса. Превыше всего он символизирует триумф разума.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            Исходя из этого следует понимать, что а) загадка сфинкса касалась Таинства Природы, а не мира Божественной Благодати, на что колесничий не сумел бы найти ответа; 6) что уровни его побед и завоеваний проявлены либо пребывают вне его сущности, а не сокрыты в его душе; в) что совершаемое им освобождение может его самого оставить в плену логического мышления; г) что испытания посвящения, из которых он вышел с честью, следует понимать физически или рационально; д) и что если бы он приблизился к колоннам Храма, между которыми восседает Верховная Жрица, то не смог бы развернуть свиток с надписью Тора, как не сумел бы ответить и на заданные ею вопросы. Царский титул персонажа не получен по праву наследования, и сам он не относится к сословию священнослужителей.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            Прорицательные значения: Помощь в трудную минуту, провидение; также война, триумф, самонадеянность, возмездие, неприятность.
            Перевернутая карта: Мятеж, ссора, спор, судебная тяжба, поражение.
            * Регалии древнееврейского первосвященника, упоминаются в библейской книге Исход (28: 30). Предположительно были прорицательным инструментом или устройством, каким-то образом облегчавшим прямой контакт с Иным миром.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="08">
        <description xml:lang="ru">
            <paragraph>
            Женщина, над головой которой парит все тот же символ жизни, виденный нами на карте Маг, закрывает пасть льву. Единственное отличие этого рисунка от привычных изображений в том, что лев уже укрощен ее благотворной силой и поводком ему служит гирлянда цветов. По причинам, которые кажутся мне вполне удовлетворительными, эта карта поменялась местами с картой Правосудие, которая обычно выступает под восьмым номером. Поскольку эта перемена мест не несет в себе ничего такого, что имело бы существенное значение для читателя, нет нужды вдаваться в объяснения. Сила в одном из ее наиболее возвышенных аспектов взаимосвязана с Божественным Таинством Единения; естественно, эта добродетель действует на всех уровнях, откуда и черпается весь символизм карты. Кроме того, она взаимосвязана с Невинностью, а также стой силой, источник которой в созерцании
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            Впрочем, ко всем этим высшим значениям мы приходим лишь путем умозаключений, и я не берусь утверждать, что они легко читаются с первого взгляда на карту. О них говорит своим потаенным языком цветочная гирлянда, которая среди всего прочего означает нежные узы и нетягостное бремя Божественного Закона, когда он принимается душой и сердцем. Эта карта не имеет никакого отношения к самоуверенности в ее обычном смысле, хотя и существуют такие предположения. Однако здесь идет речь лишь о спокойной уверенности тех, чья сила есть Бог, кто нашел в Нем свое прибежище. Существует один аспект, в котором лев означает страсти, а та, что именуется Силой, есть высшая природа освобождения от них. Она попрала ногой аспида и василиска и повергла льва и дракона.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            Прорицательные значения: Могущество, энергия, действие, отвага, великодушие; также полный успех и почет.
            Перевернутая карта: Деспотизм, злоупотребление властью, слабость, раздоры, иногда даже позор.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="09">
        <description xml:lang="ru">
            <paragraph>
            Отличие этой карты от традиционного французского варианта лишь в том, что фонарь не скрыт частично в складках плаща Отшельника, в котором явно сливаются воедино образы Древнего Днями и Света Мира. Внутри фонаря сверкает звезда. Это карта свершения, и в расширительном смысле фонарь Отшельника подобен маяку на горной вершине. Следовательно, Отшельник не является, как утверждал Кур де Жебелен, мудрецом в поисках истины и справедливости; не является он и неким особым примером опыта, как гласит позднейшее толкование. Его маяк наводит на мысль: «Там, где сейчас я, можешь быть и ты».
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            Более того, эта карта совершенно ошибочно увязывается с идеей оккультной самоизоляции как средства защиты персонального магнетизма от вмешательств извне. Этим весьма фривольным толкованием мы в числе многих других, обязаны Элифасу Леви. Оно было принято французским Орденом мартинистов, и кое-кто из нас немало слышал о Безмолвной и Неведомой Философии, отгородившейся мантией Отшельника от познания непосвященных. В подлинном мартинизме значение термина Неведомая Философия относилось к совсем иному порядку. Оно никак не связано с сохранением в секрете Учрежденных Мистерий, ни тем более с их заменителями. Напротив - как и сама карта - оно связано с той истиной, что Божественные Таинства сами оберегают себя от тех, кто недостаточно подготовлен к их восприятию.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            Прорицательные значения: Благоразумие, осмотрительность; также предательство, утайка сведений, вероломство, коррупция.
            Перевернутая карта: Сокрытие, маскировка, политика, страх, необоснованная предосторожность.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="10">
        <description xml:lang="ru">
            <paragraph>
            В этом символе я снова последовал за реконструкцией Элифаса Леви, который представил нам несколько вариантов. Обращение к египетской символике вполне закономерно, когда оно отвечает нашим целям, при условии, что в ней не заложена никакая теория относительно источника ее происхождения. Тем не менее я представил Тифона в его изначальном змеином облике. Разумеется, здесь символика не только египетская, ибо по углам карты расположились четыре существа из видения Иезекииля, да и само Колесо соответствует указанию Леви на видение Иезекииля как иллюстрацию данного ключа Таро. У этого французского оккультиста, да и в самой композиции карты, символический образ Колеса представляет вечное движение вселенной и круговращение человеческой жизни. Сфинкс означает равновесие между ними. На ободе колеса видна надпись ROTA - ни что иное, как акроним слова TAROT, причем буквы чередуются с буквами имени Бога, показывая, что Провидение вездесуще. Однако это - Божий промысел внутри, а подобный ему промысел вовне представлен Четырьмя Существами. Иногда сфинкс изображается вверху спящим на пьедестале, что совершенно искажает весь символизм, сводя на нет главную идею неподвижности в подвижном.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            За этой общей идеей, которая заложена в данном символе, скрывается отрицание случайности и фатализм. Можно добавить, что со времен Леви оккультные истолкования этой карты на редкость бессмысленны - даже для самого оккультизма. Утверждают, будто эта карта означает низшее начало, плодородие, мужскую честь, власть и т. д. Даже в интуитивных догадках обычного карточного гадания больше толку, чем в этих выдумках.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            Прорицательные значения: Судьба, удача, успех, возвышение, везение, счастье.
            Перевернутая карта: Прирост, изобилие, избыточность
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="11">
        <description xml:lang="ru">
            <paragraph>
            Поскольку эта карта строго следует традиционной символике и, прежде всего, заключает в себе все очевидные значения, о ней мало что остается сказать, кроме нескольких соображений, изложенных в первой части, к которым и может обратиться читатель.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            Тем не менее нетрудно заметить, что и эта фигура, подобно Верховной Жрице, восседает меж двух колонн, и с учетом этого желательно указать, что нравственное начало, каждому воздающее по его заслугам, - будучи, само собой, строгим аналогом высшего суда - отличается по своей сути от духовного правосудия, входящего в понятие свободы выбора. Последнее относится к мистическому порядку Провидения, в силу чего отдельным индивидам открывается постижение идеи самопосвящения высочайшим духовным ценностям. Образ действия этого правосудия подобен дуновению Духа, направленному туда, куда Ему угодно» и у нас нет ни канонов для критики, ни почвы для его объяснения. Оно подобно обладанию поэтическими дарами воображения» возвышенности и изящества. Либо они есть, либо их нет, и их наличие - столь же непостижимая тайна, сколь и отсутствие. Однако закон Правосудия не связан ни с одной из этих альтернатив. И в заключение: колонны Правосудия открывают путь в один мир, а колонны Верховной Жрицы - в другой.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            Прорицательные значения: Справедливость, правота, неподкупность, руководитель; законная и заслуженная победа.
            Перевернутая карта: Закон во всех его разновидностях, юридические осложнения, фанатизм, предубеждение, чрезмерная суровость.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="12">
        <description xml:lang="ru">
            <paragraph>
            Его виселица имеет форму тау-креста [буквы Т]. Сам же персонаж - вернее, его ноги -образуют крест-свастику. Голову этого кажущегося мученика осеняет нимб. Следует отметить, что 1) жертвенное дерево живое, ибо на нем зеленеют листья; 2) на лице персонажа выражение глубокого транса, но никак не страдания; 3) вся фигура наводит на мысль о замершей на какое-то время жизни, но все же о жизни, а не смерти. Эта карта полна глубокого скрытого значения. Один из редакторов Элифаса Леви предположил, что этого значения не знал ни сам Леви, ни его комментаторы. Символ XII ошибочно именовали картой мученичества, картой благоразумия, картой долга, картой Великого Делания. Что до меня, то я просто считаю, что карта эта выражает взаимосвязь между Божественным началом и Вселенной в одном из ее аспектов.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            Кому дано понять, что в этом символе запечатлена вся история его высшей природы, тому многое откроется о возможности великого пробуждения, и он узнает, что после священного таинства Смерти приходит светлое таинство Воскресения из мертвых.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            Прорицательные значения: Мудрость, осмотрительность, проницательность, испытания, жертва, интуиция, предсказание, пророчество.
            Перевернутая карта: Себялюбие, толпа, прозорливый человек.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="13">
        <description xml:lang="ru">
            <paragraph>
            Внешняя оболочка или маска жизни запечатлевается в постоянных переменах, трансформациях и переходах от низшего к высшему. В исправленном Таро это замечательно представлено одним из апокалиптических видений - а не грубым образом скелета с косой. За этим видением таится целый мир восхождения духа. Медленно движется окутанный тайной всадник, держа в руке черное знамя, на котором вышита Мистическая Роза, означающая жизнь. На краю горизонта меж двумя башнями сияет солнце бессмертия. Никакого видимого оружия у всадника нет, однако пред ним повергнуты на землю и король, и дитя, и юная дева, а молитвенно сложивший руки епископ покорно ждет своей участи.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            Нет нужды пояснять, что смерть, упоминавшуюся в описании предыдущей карты, следует, само собой, понимать мистически, однако к данному случаю это не относится. Естественный переход человека в следующую стадию бытия либо есть, либо может быть единой формой его прогресса. Однако необычайное и почти никому не ведомое вхождение в состояние мистической смерти -без покидания мира живых - есть перемена формы сознания и переход в состояние, к коему обычная смерть не является ни путем, ни вратами. Существующие оккультные толкования 13-й карты в целом позитивнее, чем общепринятые значения. Это возрождение, творение, место назначения, обновление и отдохновение.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            Прорицательные значения: Конец, смертность, разрушение, распад; также для мужчины - потеря благодетеля; для женщины - многочисленные противоречия; для девушки - планы замужества окончились крахом.
            Перевернутая карта: Инертность, сон, летаргия, окаменение, сомнамбулизм, крушение некоей надежды.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="14">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            A winged angel, with the sign of the sun upon his forehead and on his breast the square and triangle of the septenary. I speak of him in the masculine sense, but the figure is neither male nor female. It is held to be pouring the essences of life from chalice to chalice. It has one foot upon the earth and one upon waters, thus illustrating the nature of the essences. A direct path goes up to certain heights on the verge of the horizon, and above there is a great light, through which a crown is seen vaguely. Hereof is some part of the Secret of Eternal Life, as it is possible to man in his incarnation. All the conventional emblems are renounced herein.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            So also are the conventional meanings, which refer to changes in the seasons, perpetual movement of life and even the combination of ideas. It is, moreover, untrue to say that the figure symbolizes the genius of the sun, though it is the analogy of solar light, realized in the third part of our human triplicity. It is called Temperance fantastically, because, when the rule of it obtains in our consciousness, it tempers, combines and harmonises the psychic and material natures. Under that rule we know in our rational part something of whence we came and whither we are going.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
        <description xml:lang="ru">
            <paragraph></paragraph>
            <paragraph></paragraph>
            <paragraph></paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="15">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            The design is an accommodation, mean or harmony, between several motives mentioned in the first part. The Horned Goat of Mendes, with wings like those of a bat, is standing on an altar. At the pit of the stomach there is the sign of Mercury. The right hand is upraised and extended, being the reverse of that benediction which is given by the Hierophant in the fifth card. In the left hand there is a great flaming torch, inverted towards the earth. A reversed pentagram is on the forehead. There is a ring in front of the altar, from which two chains are carried to the necks of two figures, male and female. These are analogous with those of the fifth card, as if Adam and Eve after the Fall. Hereof is the chain and fatality of the material life.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            The figures are tailed, to signify the animal nature, but there is human intelligence in the faces, and he who is exalted above them is not to be their master for ever. Even now, he is also a bondsman, sustained by the evil that is in him and blind to the liberty of service. With more than his usual derision for the arts which he pretended to respect and interpret as a master therein, Éliphas Lévi affirms that the Baphometic figure is occult science and magic. Another commentator says that in the Divine world it signifies predestination, but there is no correspondence in that world with the things which below are of the brute. What it does signify is the Dweller on the Threshold without the Mystical Garden when those are driven forth therefrom who have eaten the forbidden fruit.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
        <description xml:lang="ru">
            <paragraph></paragraph>
            <paragraph></paragraph>
            <paragraph></paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="16">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            Occult explanations attached to this card are meagre and mostly disconcerting. It is idle to indicate that it depicts min in all its aspects, because it bears this evidence on the surface. It is said further that it contains the first allusion to a material building, but I do not conceive that the Tower is more or less material than the pillars which we have met with in three previous cases. I see nothing to warrant Papus in supposing that it is literally the fall of Adam, but there is more in favour of his alternative — that it signifies the materialization of the spiritual word. The bibliographer Christian imagines that it is the downfall of the mind, seeking to penetrate the mystery of God. I agree rather with Grand Orient that it is the ruin of the House of We, when evil has prevailed therein, and above all that it is the rending of a House of Doctrine. I understand that the reference is, however, to a House of Falsehood. It illustrates also in the most comprehensive way the old truth that "except the Lord build the house, they labour in vain that build it."
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            There is a sense in which the catastrophe is a reflection from the previous card, but not on the side of the symbolism which I have tried to indicate therein. It is more correctly a question of analogy;
            one is concerned with the fall into the material and animal state, while the other signifies destruction on the intellectual side. The Tower has been spoken of as the chastisement of pride and the intellect overwhelmed in the attempt to penetrate the Mystery of God;
            but in neither case do these explanations account for the two persons who are the living sufferers. The one is the literal word made void and the other its false interpretation. In yet a deeper sense, it may signify also the end of a dispensation, but there is no possibility here for the consideration of this involved question.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
        <description xml:lang="ru">
            <paragraph></paragraph>
            <paragraph></paragraph>
            <paragraph></paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="17">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            A great, radiant star of eight rays, surrounded by seven lesser stars — also of eight rays. The female figure in the foreground is entirely naked. Her left knee is on the land and her right foot upon the water. She pours Water of Life from two great ewers, irrigating sea and land. Behind her is rising ground and on the right a shrub or tree, whereon a bird alights. The figure expresses eternal youth and beauty. The star is l'étoile flamboyante, which appears in Masonic symbolism, but has been confused therein. That which the figure communicates to the living scene is the substance of the heavens and the elements. It has been said truly that the mottoes of this card are "Waters of Life freely" and "Gifts of the Spirit."
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            The summary of several tawdry explanations says that it is a card of hope. On other planes it has been certified as immortality and interior light. For the majority of prepared minds, the figure will appear as the type of Truth unveiled, glorious in undying beauty, pouring on the waters of the soul some part and measure of her priceless possession. But she is in reality the Great Mother in the Kabalistic Sephira Binah, which is supernal Understanding, who communicates to the Sephiroth that are below in the measure that they can receive her influx.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
        <description xml:lang="ru">
            <paragraph></paragraph>
            <paragraph></paragraph>
            <paragraph></paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="18">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            The distinction between this card and some of the conventional types is that the moon is increasing on what is called the side of mercy, to the right of the observer. It has sixteen chief and sixteen secondary rays. The card represents life of the imagination apart from life of the spirit. The path between the towers is the issue into the unknown. The dog and wolf are the fears of the natural mind in the presence of that place of exit, when there is only reflected light to guide it.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            The last reference is a key to another form of symbolism. The intellectual light is a reflection and beyond it is the unknown mystery which it cannot shew forth. It illuminates our animal nature, types of which are represented below — the dog, the wolf and that which comes up out of the deeps, the nameless and hideous tendency which is lower than the savage beast. It strives to attain manifestation, symbolized by crawling from the abyss of water to the land, but as a rule it sinks back whence it came. The face of the mind directs a calm gaze upon the unrest below;
            the dew of thought falls;
            the message is: Peace, be still;
            and it may be that there shall come a calm upon the animal nature, while the abyss beneath shall cease from giving up a form.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
        <description xml:lang="ru">
            <paragraph></paragraph>
            <paragraph></paragraph>
            <paragraph></paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="19">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            The naked child mounted on a white horse and displaying a red standard has been mentioned already as the better symbolism connected with this card. It is the destiny of the Supernatural East and the great and holy light which goes before the endless procession of humanity, coming out from the walled garden of the sensitive life and passing on the journey home. The card signifies, therefore, the transit from the manifest light of this world, represented by the glorious sun of earth, to the light of the world to come, which goes before aspiration and is typified by the heart of a child
            .</paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            But the last allusion is again the key to a different form or aspect of the symbolism. The sun is that of consciousness in the spirit - the direct as the antithesis of the reflected light. The characteristic type of humanity has become a little child therein — a child in the sense of simplicity and innocence in the sense of wisdom. In that simplicity, he bears the seal of Nature and of Art;
            in that innocence, he signifies the restored world. When the self-knowing spirit has dawned in the consciousness above the natural mind, that mind in its renewal leads forth the animal nature in a state of perfect conformity
            .</paragraph>
        </description>
        <description xml:lang="ru">
            <paragraph></paragraph>
            <paragraph></paragraph>
            <paragraph></paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="20">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            I have said that this symbol is essentially invariable in all Tarot sets, or at least the variations do not alter its character. The great angel is here encompassed by clouds, but he blows his bannered trumpet, and the cross as usual is displayed on the banner. The dead are rising from their tombs — a woman on the right, a man on the left hand, and between them their child, whose back is turned. But in this card there are more than three who are restored, and it has been thought worth while to make this variation as illustrating the insufficiency of current explanations. It should be noted that all the figures are as one in the wonder, adoration and ecstacy expressed by their attitudes. It is the card which registers the accomplishment of the great work of transformation in answer to the summons of the Supernal — which summons is heard and answered from within.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            Herein is the intimation of a significance which cannot well be carried further in the present place. What is that within us which does sound a trumpet and all that is lower in our nature rises in response — almost in a moment, almost in the twinkling of an eye? Let the card continue to depict, for those who can see no further, the Last judgment and the resurrection in the natural body;
            but let those who have inward eyes look and discover therewith. They will understand that it has been called truly in the past a card of eternal life, and for this reason it may be compared with that which passes under the name of Temperance.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
        <description xml:lang="ru">
            <paragraph></paragraph>
            <paragraph></paragraph>
            <paragraph></paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="21">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            As this final message of the Major Trumps is unchanged — and indeed unchangeable — in respect of its design, it has been partly described already regarding its deeper sense. It represents also the perfection and end of the Cosmos, the secret which is within it, the rapture of the universe when it understands itself in God. It is further the state of the soul in the consciousness of Divine Vision, reflected from the self-knowing spirit. But these meanings are without prejudice to that which I have said concerning it on the material side.
            </paragraph>
            <paragraph>
            It has more than one message on the macrocosmic side and is, for example, the state of the restored world when the law of manifestation shall have been carried to the highest degree of natural perfection. But it is perhaps more especially a story of the past, referring to that day when all was declared to be good, when the morning stars sang together and all the Sons of God shouted for joy. One of the worst explanations concerning it is that the figure symbolizes the Magus when he has reached the highest degree of initiation;
            another account says that it represents the absolute, which is ridiculous. The figure has been said to stand for Truth, which is, however, more properly allocated to the seventeenth card. Lastly, it has been called the Crown of the Magi.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
        <description xml:lang="ru">
            <paragraph></paragraph>
            <paragraph></paragraph>
            <paragraph></paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="w01">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            A hand issuing from a cloud grasps a stout wand or club.
            Divinatory Meanings: Creation, invention, enterprise, the powers which result in these;
            principle, beginning, source;
            birth, family, origin, and in a sense the virility which is behind them;
            the starting point of enterprises;
            according to another account, money, fortune, inheritance.
            Reversed: Fall, decadence, ruin, perdition, to perish also a certain clouded joy.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="w02">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            A tall man looks from a battlemented roof over sea and shore;
            he holds a globe in his right hand, while a staff in his left rests on the battlement;
            another is fixed in a ring. The Rose and Cross and Lily should be noticed on the left side.
            Divinatory Meanings: Between the alternative readings there is no marriage possible;
            on the one hand, riches, fortune, magnificence;
            on the other, physical suffering, disease, chagrin, sadness, mortification. The design gives one suggestion;
            here is a lord overlooking his dominion and alternately contemplating a globe;
            it looks like the malady, the mortification, the sadness of Alexander amidst the grandeur of this world's wealth.
            Reversed: Surprise, wonder, enchantment, emotion, trouble, fear.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="w03">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            A calm, stately personage, with his back turned, looking from a cliff's edge at ships passing over the sea. Three staves are planted in the ground, and he leans slightly on one of them.
            Divinatory Meanings: He symbolizes established strength, enterprise, effort, trade, commerce, discovery;
            those are his ships, bearing his merchandise, which are sailing over the sea. The card also signifies able co-operation in business, as if the successful merchant prince were looking from his side towards yours with a view to help you.
            Reversed: The end of troubles, suspension or cessation of adversity, toil and disappointment.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="w04">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            From the four great staves planted in the foreground there is a great garland suspended;
            two female figures uplift nosegays;
            at their side is a bridge over a moat, leading to an old manorial house.
            Divinatory Meanings: They are for once almost on the surface — country life, haven of refuge, a species of domestic harvest-home, repose, concord, harmony, prosperity, peace, and the perfected work of these.
            Reversed: The meaning remains unaltered;
            it is prosperity, increase, felicity, beauty, embellishment.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="w05">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            A posse of youths, who are brandishing staves, as if in sport or strife. It is mimic warfare, and hereto correspond the
            Divinatory Meanings: Imitation, as, for example, sham fight, but also the strenuous competition and struggle of the search after riches and fortune. In this sense it connects with the battle of life. Hence some attributions say that it is a card of gold, gain, opulence.
            Reversed: Litigation, disputes, trickery, contradiction.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="w06">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            A laurelled horseman bears one staff adorned with a laurel crown;
            footmen with staves are at his side.
            Divinatory Meanings: The card has been so designed that it can cover several significations;
            on the surface, it is a victor triumphing, but it is also great news, such as might be carried in state by the King's courier;
            it is expectation crowned with its own desire, the crown of hope, and so forth.
            Reversed: Apprehension, fear, as of a victorious enemy at the gate;
            treachery, disloyalty, as of gates being opened to the enemy;
            also indefinite delay.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="w07">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            A young man on a craggy eminence brandishing a staff;
            six other staves are raised towards him from below.
            Divinatory Meanings: It is a card of valour, for, on the surface, six are attacking one, who has, however, the vantage position. On the intellectual plane, it signifies discussion, wordy strife;
            in business — negotiations, war of trade, barter, competition. It is further a card of success, for the combatant is on the top and his enemies may be unable to reach him.
            Reversed: Perplexity, embarrassments, anxiety. It is also a caution against indecision.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="w08">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            The card represents motion through the immovable-a flight of wands through an open country;
            but they draw to the term of their course. That which they signify is at hand;
            it may be even on the threshold.
            Divinatory Meanings: Activity in undertakings, the path of such activity, swiftness, as that of an express messenger;
            great haste, great hope, speed towards an end which promises assured felicity;
            generally, that which is on the move;
            also the arrows of love.
            Reversed: Arrows of jealousy, internal dispute, stingings of conscience, quarrels;
            and domestic disputes for persons who are married.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="w09">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            The figure leans upon his staff and has an expectant look, as if awaiting an enemy. Behind are eight other staves — erect, in orderly disposition, like a palisade.
            Divinatory Meanings: The card signifies strength in opposition. If attacked, the person will meet an onslaught boldly;
            and his build shews, that he may prove a formidable antagonist. With this main significance there are all its possible adjuncts — delay, suspension, adjournment.
            Reversed: Obstacles, adversity, calamity.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="w10">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            A man oppressed by the weight of the ten staves which he is carrying.
            Divinatory Meanings: A card of many significances, and some of the readings cannot be harmonized. I set aside that which connects it with honour and good faith. The chief meaning is oppression simply, but it is also fortune, gain, any kind of success, and then it is the oppression of these things. It is also a card of false-seeming, disguise, perfidy. The place which the figure is approaching may suffer from the rods that he carries. Success is stultified if the Nine of Swords follows, and if it is a question of a lawsuit, there will be certain loss.
            Reversed: Contrarieties, difficulties, intrigues, and their analogies.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="w11">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            In a scene similar to the former, a young man stands in the act of proclamation. He is unknown but faithful, and his tidings are strange.
            Divinatory Meanings: Dark young man, faithful, a lover, an envoy, a postman. Beside a man, he will bear favourable testimony concerning him. A dangerous rival, if followed by the Page of Cups. Has the chief qualities of his suit. He may signify family intelligence.
            Reversed: Anecdotes, announcements, evil news. Also indecision and the instability which accompanies it.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="w12">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            He is shewn as if upon a journey, armed with a short wand, and although mailed is not on a warlike errand. He is passing mounds or pyramids. The motion of the horse is a key to the character of its rider, and suggests the precipitate mood, or things connected therewith.
            Divinatory Meanings: Departure, absence, flight, emigration. A dark young man, friendly. Change of residence.
            Reversed: Rupture, division, interruption, discord.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="w13">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            The Wands throughout this suit are always in leaf, as it is a suit of life and animation. Emotionally and otherwise, the Queen's personality corresponds to that of the King, but is more magnetic.
            Divinatory Meanings: A dark woman, countrywoman, friendly, chaste, loving, honourable. If the card beside her signifies a man, she is well disposed towards him;
            if a woman, she is interested in the Querent. Also, love of money, or a certain success in business.
            Reversed: Good, economical, obliging, serviceable. Signifies also — but in certain positions and in the neighbourhood of other cards tending in such directions — opposition, jealousy, even deceit and infidelity.
            </paragraph>

        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="w14">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            The physical and emotional nature to which this card is attributed is dark, ardent, lithe, animated, impassioned, noble. The King uplifts a flowering wand, and wears, like his three correspondences in the remaining suits, what is called a cap of maintenance beneath his crown. He connects with the symbol of the lion, which is emblazoned on the back of his throne.
            Divinatory Meanings: Dark man, friendly, countryman, generally married, honest and conscientious. The card always signifies honesty, and may mean news concerning an unexpected heritage to fall in before very long.
            Reversed: Good, but severe;
            austere, yet tolerant.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="c01">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            The waters are beneath, and thereon are water-lilies;
            the hand issues from the cloud, holding in its palm the cup, from which four streams are pouring;
            a dove, bearing in its bill a cross-marked Host, descends to place the Wafer in the Cup;
            the dew of water is falling on all sides. It is an intimation of that which may lie behind the Lesser Arcana.
            Divinatory Meanings: House of the true heart, joy, content, abode, nourishment, abundance, fertility;
            Holy Table, felicity hereof.
            Reversed: House of the false heart, mutation, instability, revolution.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="c02">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            A youth and maiden are pledging one another, and above their cups rises the Caduceus of Hermes, between the great wings of which there appears a lion's head. It is a variant of a sign which is found in a few old examples of this card. Some curious emblematical meanings are attached to it, but they do not concern us in this place.
            Divinatory Meanings: Love, passion, friendship, affinity, union, concord, sympathy, the interrelation of the sexes, and — as a suggestion apart from all offices of divination — that desire which is not in Nature, but by which Nature is sanctified.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="c03">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            Maidens in a garden-ground with cups uplifted, as if pledging one another.
            Divinatory Meanings: The conclusion of any matter in plenty, perfection and merriment;
            happy issue, victory, fulfilment, solace, healing,
            Reversed: Expedition, dispatch, achievement, end. It signifies also the side of excess in physical enjoyment, and the pleasures of the senses.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="c04">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            A young man is seated under a tree and contemplates three cups set on the grass before him;
            an arm issuing from a cloud offers him another cup. His expression notwithstanding is one of discontent with his environment.
            Divinatory Meanings: Weariness, disgust, aversion, imaginary vexations, as if the wine of this world had caused satiety only;
            another wine, as if a fairy gift, is now offered the wastrel, but he sees no consolation therein. This is also a card of blended pleasure.
            Reversed: Novelty, presage, new instruction, new relations.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="c05">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            A dark, cloaked figure, looking sideways at three prone cups two others stand upright behind him;
            a bridge is in the background, leading to a small keep or holding. Divanatory Meanings: It is a card of loss, but something remains over;
            three have been taken, but two are left;
            it is a card of inheritance, patrimony, transmission, but not corresponding to expectations;
            with some interpreters it is a card of marriage, but not without bitterness or frustration.
            Reversed: News, alliances, affinity, consanguinity, ancestry, return, false projects.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="c06">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            Children in an old garden, their cups filled with flowers.
            Divinatory Meanings: A card of the past and of memories, looking back, as — for example — on childhood;
            happiness, enjoyment, but coming rather from the past;
            things that have vanished. Another reading reverses this, giving new relations, new knowledge, new environment, and then the children are disporting in an unfamiliar precinct.
            Reversed: The future, renewal, that which will come to pass presently.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="c07">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            Strange chalices of vision, but the images are more especially those of the fantastic spirit.
            Divinatory Meanings: Fairy favours, images of reflection, sentiment, imagination, things seen in the glass of contemplation;
            some attainment in these degrees, but nothing permanent or substantial is suggested.
            Reversed: Desire, will, determination, project.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="c08">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            A man of dejected aspect is deserting the cups of his felicity, enterprise, undertaking or previous concern.
            Divinatory Meanings: The card speaks for itself on the surface, but other readings are entirely antithetical — giving joy, mildness, timidity, honour, modesty. In practice, it is usually found that the card shews the decline of a matter, or that a matter which has been thought to be important is really of slight consequence — either for good or evil.
            Reversed: Great joy, happiness, feasting.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="c09">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            A goodly personage has feasted to his heart's content, and abundant refreshment of wine is on the arched counter behind him, seeming to indicate that the future is also assured. The picture offers the material side only, but there are other aspects.
            Divinatory Meanings: Concord, contentment, physical bien-être;
            also victory, success, advantage;
            satisfaction for the Querent or person for whom the consultation is made.
            Reversed: Truth, loyalty, liberty;
            but the readings vary and include mistakes, imperfections, etc.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="c10">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            Appearance of Cups in a rainbow;
            it is contemplated in wonder and ecstacy by a man and woman below, evidently husband and wife. His right arm is about her;
            his left is raised upward;
            she raises her right arm. The two children dancing near them have not observed the prodigy but are happy after their own manner.
            There is a home-scene beyond.
            Divinatory Meanings: Contentment, repose of the entire heart;
            the perfection of that state;
            also perfection of human love and friendship;
            if with several picture-cards, a person who is taking charge of the Querent's interests;
            also the town, village or country inhabited by the Querent.
            Reversed: Repose of the false heart, indignation, violence.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="c11">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            A fair, pleasing, somewhat effeminate page, of studious and intent aspect, contemplates a fish rising from a cup to look at him. It is the pictures of the mind taking form.
            Divinatory Meanings: Fair young man, one impelled to render service and with whom the Querent will be connected;
            a studious youth;
            news, message;
            application, reflection, meditation;
            also these things directed to business.
            Reversed: Taste, inclination, attachment, seduction, deception, artifice.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="c12">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            Graceful, but not warlike;
            riding quietly, wearing a winged helmet, referring to those higher graces of the imagination which sometimes characterize this card. He too is a dreamer, but the images of the side of sense haunt him in his vision.
            Divinatory Meanings: Arrival, approach — sometimes that of a messenger;
            advances, proposition, demeanour, invitation, incitement.
            Reversed: Trickery, artifice, subtlety, swindling, duplicity, fraud.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="c13">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            Beautiful, fair, dreamy — as one who sees visions in a cup. This is, however, only one of her aspects;
            she sees, but she also acts, and her activity feeds her dream.
            Divinatory Meanings: Good, fair woman;
            honest, devoted woman, who will do service to the Querent;
            loving intelligence, and hence the gift of vision;
            success, happiness, pleasure;
            also wisdom, virtue;
            a perfect spouse and a good mother.
            Reversed: The accounts vary;
            good woman;
            otherwise, distinguished woman but one not to be trusted;
            perverse woman;
            vice, dishonour, depravity.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="c14">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            He holds a short sceptre in his left hand and a great cup in his right;
            his throne is set upon the sea;
            on one side a ship is riding and on the other a dolphin is leaping. The implicit is that the Sign of the Cup naturally refers to water, which appears in all the court cards.
            Divinatory Meanings: Fair man, man of business, law, or divinity;
            responsible, disposed to oblige the Querent;
            also equity, art and science, including those who profess science, law and art;
            creative intelligence.
            Reversed: Dishonest, double-dealing man;
            roguery, exaction, injustice, vice, scandal, pillage, considerable loss.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>

    <card id="s01">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            A hand issues from a cloud, grasping as word, the point of which is encircled by a crown.
            Divinatory Meanings: Triumph, the excessive degree in everything, conquest, triumph of force. It is a card of great force, in love as well as in hatred. The crown may carry a much higher significance than comes usually within the sphere of fortune-telling.
            Reversed: The same, but the results are disastrous;
            another account says — conception, childbirth, augmentation, multiplicity.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="s02">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            A hoodwinked female figure balances two swords upon her shoulders.
            Divinatory Meanings: Conformity and the equipoise which it suggests, courage, friendship, concord in a state of arms;
            another reading gives tenderness, affection, intimacy. The suggestion of harmony and other favourable readings must be considered in a qualified manner, as Swords generally are not symbolical of beneficent forces in human affairs.
            Reversed: Imposture, falsehood, duplicity, disloyalty.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="s03">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            Three swords piercing a heart;
            cloud and rain behind.
            Divinatory Meanings: Removal, absence, delay, division, rupture, dispersion, and all that the design signifies naturally, being too simple and obvious to call for specific enumeration.
            Reversed: Mental alienation, error, loss, distraction, disorder, confusion.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="s04">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            The effigy of a knight in the attitude of prayer, at full length upon his tomb.
            Divinatory Meanings: Vigilance, retreat, solitude, hermit's repose, exile, tomb and coffin. It is these last that have suggested the design.
            Reversed: Wise administration, circumspection, economy, avarice, precaution, testament.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="s05">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            A disdainful man looks after two retreating and dejected figures. Their swords lie upon the ground. He carries two others on his left shoulder, and a third sword is in his right hand, point to earth. He is the master in possession of the field.
            Divinatory Meanings: Degradation, destruction, revocation, infamy, dishonour, loss, with the variants and analogues of these.
            Reversed: The same;
            burial and obsequies.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="s06">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            A ferryman carrying passengers in his punt to the further shore. The course is smooth, and seeing that the freight is light, it may be noted that the work is not beyond his strength.
            Divinatory Meanings: journey by water, route, way, envoy, commissionary, expedient.
            Reversed: Declaration, confession, publicity;
            one account says that it is a proposal of love.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="s07">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            A man in the act of carrying away five swords rapidly;
            the two others of the card remain stuck in the ground. A camp is close at hand.
            Divinatory Meanings: Design, attempt, wish, hope, confidence;
            also quarrelling, a plan that may fail, annoyance. The design is uncertain in its import, because the significations are widely at variance with each other.
            Reversed: Good advice, counsel, instruction, slander, babbling.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="s08">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            A woman, bound and hoodwinked, with the swords of the card about her. Yet it is rather a card of temporary durance than of irretrievable bondage.
            Divinatory Meanings: Bad news, violent chagrin, crisis, censure, power in trammels, conflict, calumny;
            also sickness.
            Reversed: Disquiet, difficulty, opposition, accident, treachery;
            what is unforeseen;
            fatality.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="s09">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            One seated on her couch in lamentation, with the swords over her. She is as one who knows no sorrow which is like unto hers. It is a card of utter desolation.
            Divinatory Meanings: Death, failure, miscarriage, delay, deception, disappointment, despair.
            Reversed: Imprisonment, suspicion, doubt, reasonable fear, shame.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="s10">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            A prostrate figure, pierced by all the swords belonging to the card.
            Divinatory Meanings: Whatsoever is intimated by the design;
            also pain, affliction, tears, sadness, desolation. It is not especially a card of violent death.
            Reversed: Advantage, profit, success, favour, but none of these are permanent;
            also power and authority.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="s11">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            A lithe, active figure holds a sword upright in both hands, while in the act of swift walking. He is passing over rugged land, and about his way the clouds are collocated wildly. He is alert and lithe, looking this way and that, as if an expected enemy might appear at any moment.
            Divinatory Meanings: Authority, overseeing, secret service, vigilance, spying, examination, and the qualities thereto belonging.
            Reversed: More evil side of these qualities;
            what is unforeseen, unprepared state;
            sickness is also intimated.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="s12">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            He is riding in full course, as if scattering his enemies. In the design he is really a prototypical hero of romantic chivalry. He might almost be Galahad, whose sword is swift and sure because he is clean of heart.
            Divinatory Meanings: Skill, bravery, capacity, defence, address, enmity, wrath, war, destruction, opposition, resistance, ruin. There is therefore a sense in which the card signifies death, but it carries this meaning only in its proximity to other cards of fatality.
            Reversed: Imprudence, incapacity, extravagance.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="s13">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            Her right hand raises the weapon vertically and the hilt rests on an arm of her royal chair the left hand is extended, the arm raised her countenance is severe but chastened;
            it suggests familiarity with sorrow. It does not represent mercy, and, her sword notwithstanding, she is scarcely a symbol of power.
            Divinatory Meanings: Widowhood, female sadness and embarrassment, absence, sterility, mourning, privation, separation.
            Reversed: Malice, bigotry, artifice, prudery, bale, deceit.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="s14">

        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            He sits in judgment, holding the unsheathed sign of his suit. He recalls, of course, the conventional Symbol of justice in the Trumps Major, and he may represent this virtue, but he is rather the power of life and death, in virtue of his office.
            Divinatory Meanings: Whatsoever arises out of the idea of judgment and all its connexions-power, command, authority, militant intelligence, law, offices of the crown, and so forth.
            Reversed: Cruelty, perversity, barbarity, perfidy, evil intention.
            </paragraph>
        </description>

    </card>

    <card id="p01">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            A hand — issuing, as usual, from a cloud — holds up a pentacle.
            Divinatory Meanings: Perfect contentment, felicity, ecstasy;
            also speedy intelligence;
            gold.
            Reversed: The evil side of wealth, bad intelligence;
            also great riches. In any case it shews prosperity, comfortable material conditions, but whether these are of advantage to the possessor will depend on whether the card is reversed or not.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="p02">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            A young man, in the act of dancing, has a pentacle in either hand, and they are joined by that endless cord which is like the number 8 reversed.
            Divinatory Meanings: On the one hand it is represented as a card of gaiety, recreation and its connexions, which is the subject of the design;
            but it is read also as news and messages in writing, as obstacles, agitation, trouble, embroilment.
            Reversed: Enforced gaiety, simulated enjoyment, literal sense, handwriting, composition, letters of exchange.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="p03">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            A sculptor at his work in a monastery. Compare the design which illustrates the Eight of Pentacles. The apprentice or amateur therein has received his reward and is now at work in earnest.
            Divinatory Meanings: Métier, trade, skilled labour;
            usually, however, regarded as a card of nobility, aristocracy, renown, glory.
            Reversed: Mediocrity, in work and otherwise, puerility, pettiness, weakness.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="p04">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            A crowned figure, having a pentacle over his crown, clasps another with hands and arms;
            two pentacles are under his feet. He holds to that which he has.
            Divinatory Meanings: The surety of possessions, cleaving to that which one has, gift, legacy, inheritance.
            Reversed: Suspense, delay, opposition.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="p05">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            Two mendicants in a snow-storm pass a lighted casement.
            Divinatory Meanings: The card foretells material trouble above all, whether in the form illustrated — that is, destitution — or otherwise. For some cartomancists, it is a card of love and lovers-wife, husband, friend, mistress;
            also concordance, affinities. These alternatives cannot be harmonized.
             Reversed: Disorder, chaos, ruin, discord, profligacy.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="p06">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            A person in the guise of a merchant weighs money in a pair of scales and distributes it to the needy and distressed. It is a testimony to his own success in life, as well as to his goodness of heart.
            Divinatory Meanings: Presents, gifts, gratification another account says attention, vigilance now is the accepted time, present prosperity, etc.
            Reversed: Desire, cupidity, envy, jealousy, illusion.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="p07">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            A young man, leaning on his staff, looks intently at seven pentacles attached to a clump of greenery on his right;
            one would say that these were his treasures and that his heart was there.
            Divinatory Meanings: These are exceedingly contradictory;
            in the main, it is a card of money, business, barter;
            but one reading gives altercation, quarrels — and another innocence, ingenuity, purgation.
            Reversed: Cause for anxiety regarding money which it may be proposed to lend.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="p08">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            An artist in stone at his work, which he exhibits in the form of trophies.
            Divinatory Meanings: Work, employment, commission, craftsmanship, skill in craft and business, perhaps in the preparatory stage.
            Reversed: Voided ambition, vanity, cupidity, exaction, usury. It may also signify the possession of skill, in the sense of the ingenious mind turned to cunning and intrigue.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="p09">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            A woman, with a bird upon her wrist, stands amidst a great abundance of grapevines in the garden of a manorial house. It is a wide domain, suggesting plenty in all things. Possibly it is her own possession and testifies to material well-being.
            Divinatory Meanings: Prudence, safety, success, accomplishment, certitude, discernment.
            Reversed: Roguery, deception, voided project, bad faith.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="p10">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            A man and woman beneath an archway which gives entrance to a house and domain. They are accompanied by a child, who looks curiously at two dogs accosting an ancient personage seated in the foreground. The child's hand is on one of them.
            Divinatory Meanings: Gain, riches;
            family matters, archives, extraction, the abode of a family.
            Reversed: Chance, fatality, loss, robbery, games of hazard;
            sometimes gift, dowry, pension.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="p11">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            A youthful figure, looking intently at the pentacle which hovers over his raised hands. He moves slowly, insensible of that which is about him.
            Divinatory Meanings: Application, study, scholarship, reflection another reading says news, messages and the bringer thereof;
            also rule, management.
            Reversed: Prodigality, dissipation, liberality, luxury;
            unfavourable news.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="p12">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            He rides a slow, enduring, heavy horse, to which his own aspect corresponds. He exhibits his symbol, but does not look therein.
            Divinatory Meanings: Utility, serviceableness, interest, responsibility, rectitude-all on the normal and external plane.
            Reversed: inertia, idleness, repose of that kind, stagnation;
            also placidity, discouragement, carelessness.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="p13">
        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            The face suggests that of a dark woman, whose qualities might be summed up in the idea of greatness of soul;
            she has also the serious cast of intelligence;
            she contemplates her symbol and may see worlds therein.
            Divinatory Meanings: Opulence, generosity, magnificence, security, liberty.
            Reversed: Evil, suspicion, suspense, fear, mistrust.
            </paragraph>
        </description>
    </card>
    <card id="p14">

        <description xml:lang="en">
            <paragraph>
            The figure calls for no special description the face is rather dark, suggesting also courage, but somewhat lethargic in tendency. The bull's head should be noted as a recurrent symbol on the throne. The sign of this suit is represented throughout as engraved or blazoned with the pentagram, typifying the correspondence of the four elements in human nature and that by which they may be governed. In many old Tarot packs this suit stood for current coin, money, deniers. I have not invented the substitution of pentacles and I have no special cause to sustain in respect of the alternative. But the consensus of
            divinatory meanings is on the side of some change, because the cards do not happen to deal especially with questions of money.
            Divinatory Meanings: Valour, realizing intelligence, business and normal intellectual aptitude, sometimes mathematical gifts and attainments of this kind;
            success in these paths.
            Reversed: Vice, weakness, ugliness, perversity, corruption, peril.
            </paragraph>
        </description>

    </card>
</deck>